<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bushido | Software Samurai]]></title>
  <link href="http://CptnKirk.github.io/blog/categories/bushido/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://CptnKirk.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-07T08:23:39-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://CptnKirk.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jim Hazen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cultivating a Hacker Culture: The Culture]]></title>
    <link href="http://CptnKirk.github.io/blog/2013/06/04/cultivating-a-hacker-culture-the-culture/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-04T10:28:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://CptnKirk.github.io/blog/2013/06/04/cultivating-a-hacker-culture-the-culture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Previously I wrote about the hacker.  The warrior of the digital age.  In this post I&rsquo;ll explore the hacker culture. When I think about those whom I associate with being members of the hacker culture I think about a few hacker hallmarks:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Solve a problem.  There are so many problems to be solved and hackers are innate problem solvers. Within the Open Source movement, hacker are free to solve the problems that interest them. In the corporate world they thrive in tackling the hardest problems.  Often working with fellow hackers on innovative solutions.</p></li>
<li><p>Knowledge and information are the lifeblood of achievement and this knowledge must be freely available.  Hackers get a bad rap for being anti-social nerds.  But the truth is that they&rsquo;re often highly social.  The Open Source and Free Software movement demonstrated how hackers from around the world could collaborate together to disrupt and improve the nature of software development.</p></li>
<li><p>The Meritocracy.  The hacker culture at it&rsquo;s core is a meritocracy.  A hacker&rsquo;s accomplishments, his improvements to the culture are his currency.  This promotes the sharing of ideas and the improvement of existing conditions in order to gain the recognition (or sometimes just personal satisfaction) of the community. The more people that use and benefit from your creation the greater the value of that creation.</p></li>
<li><p>Whatever you&rsquo;re doing, be great at it.  You don&rsquo;t have to be a coder to be a hacker.  I&rsquo;ve seen many a DevOps, CQ and PM embody the hacker ideals.</p></li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<p>Originally when I started writing this, I had &ldquo;being great (leet/1337)&rdquo; at number one.  But when I thought about it a bit more and realized that at their core hackers are problem solvers.  While hackers to train themselves in the art of clean and performant code, it&rsquo;s typically the problem that drives the hacker and solving the problem is often more important than solving the problem with a lot of &ldquo;perfection&rdquo; overhead.  I suppose that perfection is in the eye of the beholder, but let&rsquo;s just say that I&rsquo;ve seen a lot of problem solved with less than perfect code.</p>

<p>Knowledge is another aspect of the hacker culture.  Knowledge is often the byproduct of invention that fuels the next invention.  Hackers tend to be generous with their knowledge.  Just look at how many blogs like this one seek to spread knowledge.  This blog is written by a hacker, developed with the aid of a publishing tool developed by another hacker and hosted for free by a company run by hackers.  Hopefully the ideas and (soon to be) code contained within this blog will contribute to the knowledge of others and help fuel their creations.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to skip Meritocracy and being great for now.  I&rsquo;ve spent a lot of words, possibly just talking to myself.  The goal however to talk to those just getting started, or those that want more but don&rsquo;t know how or where to start; to help cultivate and contribute to a hacker culture.  It&rsquo;s not really difficult to be a hacker.  Listen, read, gain knowledge, solve a few problems and then teach/show others what you&rsquo;ve learned.  You&rsquo;ll start to gain the respect and appreciation of those you&rsquo;ve helped along the way.  As you solve problems your problem solving skills will improve and you&rsquo;ll find yourself becoming quite good at your chosen art.</p>

<p>Some tips to get you started:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Find something you enjoy, or a problem you wish you didn&rsquo;t have.  Then build towards that goal.  You may not be able to solve your problem in a night or a weekend, but you can start gaining knowledge right way.  Read up on your subject matter, use the knowledge of those that have come before.  Then start to contribute.  Even if it&rsquo;s just a rambling blog site on your current struggle.  You&rsquo;ll be surprised how many people we share struggles with.</p></li>
<li><p>Invest in personal performance.  Improving your knowledge is great, but being able to apply your knowledge at the speed of thought can be magical.  Invest in learning the tools of your craft.  Learn a text editing program like VIM or Emacs and if you&rsquo;re using an IDE for development, learn the shortcut keys to accelerate common tasks.  It is worth being slower than normal for a few days while you learn.  The speed increases over time more than make up for it.</p></li>
<li><p>Find a community and participate.  You are not alone.  There are many people that share your interests and/or problems.  You&rsquo;ll be amazed at how willing these communities are to help.  Take their help and in return, contribute.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cultivating a Hacker Culture: The Hacker]]></title>
    <link href="http://CptnKirk.github.io/blog/2013/06/01/cultivating-a-hacker-culture-the-hacker/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-01T23:46:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://CptnKirk.github.io/blog/2013/06/01/cultivating-a-hacker-culture-the-hacker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m the type of person who is constantly looking at new technology or ways of developing software.  I&rsquo;m always looking for the next big thing that will allow me to do something I couldn&rsquo;t before, or do the same stuff quicker or easier.  I&rsquo;ve recently been attracted to watching YouTube presentations on whatever it is that&rsquo;s on my mind.  Recently something got me thinking.  Nearly all of the best presentations are given by a class of developers that I associate with being &ldquo;hackers&rdquo;.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p>What&rsquo;s a &ldquo;hacker&rdquo; to me?  If you&rsquo;ve ever seen the movie Hackers (<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0113243/">http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0113243/</a>), that&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;m talking about.  A class of developer with a thirst for knowledge and ability.  Driven to be &ldquo;elite&rdquo; and to have their abilities recognized.  Here are a couple examples of some Erlang hackers.  The two talks are valuable in general, even if you aren&rsquo;t interested in Erlang (and if you aren&rsquo;t interested in Erlang, you probably should be :&ndash;)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mGKMq0Cyiks">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mGKMq0Cyiks</a> &mdash; Erlang: Noob to production in 2 months
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8BNpOHFvg_Q">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8BNpOHFvg_Q</a> &mdash; Lager: Logging with confidence</p>

<p>One shows how a hacker developed and deployed some web based chat services to his community in a couple months.  The other shows how a hacker decided to improve the logging standard that he was forced to work with; and by doing so elevated the state of the art for an entire community.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve recently been discussing continuous integration with my co-workers.  To most hacker cultures this is simply a given; the first presenter talks about his continuous build/deploy process.  He was pimping Erlang&rsquo;s hot code deployment and &ldquo;telnet to the VM&rdquo; capabilities, continuous integration was a given but he briefly discussed his setup.</p>

<p>So where am I going with this?  I&rsquo;ve come to realize that I respect and admire a lot of &ldquo;hacker&rdquo; qualities.  I want more of that, I want to embody more of that, and I love working with people that have similar aspirations and values.</p>

<p>Up next.  The Hacker and The Hacker Culture.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
